Benjamin Smith Barton Papers 1789-1815 Mss.B.B284d
American Philosophical Society
- Series II. Subject files, ca.1789-1815; 7 boxes; 3.5 linear feet (Box 7-13)
  - Miscellaneous notes and manuscripts
    - United States President
      - Message (publication) about Treaty of Ghent, 1814 Dec. 1; 1 item (84 p.)
    - Vaughan, John
      - Aya Pana, n.d.; 1 item
      - Note of volumes sent to the Linnean Society of London, 1802 June 8; 1 item
      - Note to Benjamin Smith Barton on A.P.S. business, 1806 Jan. 27; 1 item
        Note by Barton on reverse.
      - Population of Spain taken from 1803 Census, n.d.; 1 item
    - Will of Dr. Benjamin Smith Barton (typescript), n.d.; 1 item (4 p.)
    - Withinson, Thomas J.
      - Memo to Benjamin Smith Barton, n.d.; 1 item
    - Young Ladies Academy of Philadelphia
      - Meeting notice, 1814 March 23; 1 item
- Series III. Bound volumes, 1790-1826; 32 vols.; 2 lin. feet
  Bound volumes of manuscript notes on various scientific topics, including a commonplace book, generation, fevers, mineralogy, and journals of trips taken by Barton to New York state, Virginia, and Pennsylvania.
  - Account Book, 1805-1806; 1; 1 vol. (16 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Chemistry notebooks, n.d.; 2; 6 vol.s (426 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Commonplace book, n.d.; 3; 1 vol. (84 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Discussion of Seneca Indians, their canoes and vocabulary, mosquitoes, black rock, big teeth, and Niagara Falls.
  - Sulphur Springs, n.d.; 4; 1 vol. (30 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Concerning Water, n.d.; 5; 1 vol. (20 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Expense notebook, 1825 Oct. 4-1826 Jan. 7; 6; 1 vol. (34 p.)
    Enclosed note suggests this might be the notebook of a Wm. Bradford, whose name is found on the back of the notebook (J. Ewan, 1972). Barton cannot be the author, since these accounts were kept after his death.
  - Journal of upper New York trip, 1799 June 9-1799 July 3; 7; 1 vol. (88 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Journal of Virginia trip, n.d.; 8; 1 vol. (41 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Journal of a trip up the Hudson, n.d.; 9; 1 vol. ( 92 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Covers a wide range of topics including climate, soil, and the first instance of intoxication among the Indians of New York. Undoubtedly the most provocative entry is "Remarkable Tradition of the Mahicans," which suggested that cannibalism was practiced during a "calamitous period" of famine.
    Though the journal is undated, a rough draft on Mohicans dated March 18, 1797, is enclosed.
  - Notes of trip through N.J. and Pa, 1802 June 30-1802 July 12; 10; 1 vol. (20 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Latin words and definitions, 11; 1 vol. (14 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Lecture on botany, n.d.; 12; 1 vol. (37 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Lecture on water and ice, 13; 1 vol. (24 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Lecture on fire, heat, light, n.d.; 14; 1 vol. (42 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Meteorological observations, 1790 Jan. 1-1791 Sept. 13; 15; 1 vol. (24 p.); Bartram, William
  - Botanical notebook, n.d.; 16; 1 vol. (45 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Notebook on "intermittent" fevers, 1793 Jan. 9-1793 Nov. 29; 17; 1 vol. (34 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Notebook on fevers -- causes and prevention of. Also mention the "vapour."
  - Notebook on mineralogy, n.d.; 18; 1 vol. (26 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Notebook on quadrapeds, n.d.; 19; 1 vol. (37 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Notebook on water, n.d.; 20; 1 vol. (26 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Notebooks on air, n.d.; 21; 2 vol.s (34 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Notes on a N.Y. tour, n.d.; 22; 1 vol. (12 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Theory of generation, n.d.; 23; 1 vol. (10 p.); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Zoological notebook, 1793 Dec. 24-1794 June 17; 24; 1 vol. (99 p. ); Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Also, an enclosed note on the muskrat dated January 3, 1808.
  - Compendium botanicum ad notition..., 1809 Oct. 23 (received); 25; 1 vol. (141 p.)
  - Memoir on the effects of cold, 1796 Feb.-1796 March; 26; 1 vol. (20 p.); L'Heritier, Charles Latour
  - Meteorological observations, 1799 July 9-1799 Dec. 27; 27; 1 vol. (61 p.)
  - Notebook on Insects, n.d.; 28; 1 vol. (92 p.)
  - Observations concerning the nature of animal life, n.d.; 29; 1 vol. (82 p.)
    Previous record stated that the vol. was written by a student.
  - Essay on Eupatorium perfoliatium., 1812 Nov. 18; 30; 1 vol. (30 p.); Potter, Nathaniel
  - Student's medical and scientific lecture notes, 31; 1 vol. (128 p.)
  - Report to Henry Knox on Creek Indians, etc., 1791 May 2; 32; 1 vol. (43 p.); Swan, Caleb.
    Printed: Schoolcraft. Historical and Statistical Information... (970.1: Sch, vol. 5, 251-83).
- Series IV. Graphic materials, 1773-ca.1815; 2 boxes; 0.75 linear feet
  Pen and watercolor drawings and engravings of botanical and natural historical subjects by Barton, but also including 64 sketches by William Bartram, three illustrations of rattlesnake anatomy attributed to Benjamin Henry Latrobe, and other works by Frederick Pursh,Pierre Turpin, and other artists.
  Native American Images note: Fifteen engravings, watercolor sketches, pen and ink sketches, and copper printing plates of Native American portraits, artifacts and hieroglyphics attributed to Barton, ca. 1790-1810. Scientific in nature, the images reflect animal figures of the Algonquian and portraits of Seminole and Cherokee Indians. Illustrations collected by Barton include William Bartram’s portrait of Mico-Chlucco, King of the Muscogulges, John H. Hopkin’s watercolor sketch of two arrow heads, and a copper plate of Lewis and Clark’s Shahaka, the Mandan chief. Referenced in Freeman’s Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian at the APS and Murphy Smith’s Historical American Sketches.
  Taxonomic Identifications note: Some generalized taxonomic identifications of illustrations were made by person(s) unknown at undetermined times, but which have since been reidentified. The reidentifications are noted as part of the item title, but the items remain in the order as originally identified so as to preserve that original order and their misidentifications. Revised identifications were provided 15 May 2012.
  - Amaryllis lutea, n.d.; 1 colored print
    Print from Bot. Mag. t. 290
  - Animal qui Produit le Musc. Het Muscus-Dier, n.d.; 1 engraving
    Musk deer. J. V. Schley direx.
  - Adonis autumnalis, n.d.; 1 colored engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Plate 135.
  - Aescuclus parviflora Walt, n.d.; 1 pencil and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Aesculus capsules, n.d.; 1 print; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Previously attributed to William Bartram
  - Alligator, or Hell-bender [reidentification: hellbender, a type of salamander (amphibian, not reptile)], 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Salamander
  - Alligator, or Hell-bender [reidentification: hellbender, a type of salamander (amphibian, not reptile)], 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Anatomical torso, n.d.; 1 print; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Antelope [reidentification: pronghorn], n.d.; 1 pen and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Note on previous folder suggested that the drawing was not Barton's but perhaps the work of Charles Willson Peale.
  - Antlers [reidentification: probably caribou], n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    "From Labrador."
  - Asplenium platyneuron, 1809 July; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    "Schuylkill, July, 1809"
  - Badger? [reidentification: badger], n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Bean, and shoot?, 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Elements, pl. V, figs. M,N,O.
  - Bone [leg?], fossil, n.d.; 1 pastel; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Bones, and sockets [reidentification: knee joint; articulation of femur with tibia and fibula, possibly human], 1 charcoal sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Brutae [reidentification: skull of a sciurid, possibly a groundhog, with overgrown upper incisors resulting from malocculsion with the lower incisors], 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    "Upper jaw [skull] of an unknown animal of the order of Brutae found on the surface of the Little levels of Greenbriar."
  - Brutae (upper jaw), found at Greenbriar [reidentification: skull of a sciurid, possibly a groundhog, with overgrown upper incisors resulting from malocculsion with the lower incisors], 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Brutae [upper jaw], found at Greenbriar [reidentification: skull of a sciurid, possibly a groundhog, with overgrown upper incisors resulting from malocculsion with the lower incisors], 1 pen and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Campsis, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    "A Chinese vine."
  - Chamaelirium luteum (L.) Gray, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Chimaphila umbellata var. Cisatlantica Blake., n.d.; 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Called Pyrola maculata
  - Clethra acuminata Michx., n.d.; 1 pencil sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Conifer Seedling. Taxodium distichum, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Cyrilla racemiflora L., n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Datura stramonium L., n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Delphinium exaltatum Ait., n.d.; 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Description of a new North American plant, n.d.; 1 item; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Diplacus glutinosus (Wendl.), 1 pencil and watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Nuttall, VII. 8.
  - Dog of the American Indians, 1 engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    "Signed BS Barton backwards in bottom of right-hand corner."
    Separated Materials note
    APS has the copper plate for this engraving.
  - Epilobium angustifolium, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Broad Mountain.
  - "Fern." Polypodium vulgare, n.d.; 1 print; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Fungal sporophore, 1812 March 29; 1 print; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Fungi, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Six figures
  - Fungus, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    "Exact size of life and natural colours. found in Mr. Bartram's garden? Had a very fetid smell."
  - Fungus, 1809 June 24; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Fungus, tree, or anatomical part ?, n.d.; 1 print; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Heart, 1786; 1 engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Heart and blood vessels, 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Hieracium venosum L.?, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Illicium floridanum Ellis, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Indian artifacts, 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    "Taken out of an Indian grave, in the country of the Five Nations..."
  - Indian hieroglyphs?, 1 ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Internal organs, 1784; 1 item; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Sketch of dissection.
  - Internal organs, 1784; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Intestines, supported by mesenteries, n.d.; 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Intestines, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Jaw bone (canid?) [reidentification: opossum, lower jaw], n.d.; 1 pen and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Knee joint, n.d.; 1 item; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Lepidodendron, 1 ink and watercolor drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Carboniferous Lycopsid.
  - Liliaceous genus from William Hamilton's "Stove"?, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Mammoth tooth [reidentification: molar of mammoth or elephant], n.d.; 3 watercolors; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Two sketches with lateral and crown views, one sketch with crown view only.
  - Mastodon lower jaw and teeth, fossil, 1 pencil drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Dorsal view.
  - Mastodon lower jaw and teeth, fossil, 1 pencil sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Lateral view
  - Mastodon tooth [reidentification: mastodon molar], n.d.; 2 pencil drawings; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    One lateral view, one crown view.
  - Mastodon tusk, n.d.; 1 item; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Medeola virginiana L., n.d.; 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Melothria pendula L., 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Mitchella repens, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Mole [reidentification: short-tailed shrew], n.d.; 1 engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    APS owns the copperplate.
  - Mole (jaws and teeth) [reidentifications: beaver; muskrat or vole], 3 watercolor and ink drawings; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Mole (ventral view) [reidentification: gopher], n.d.; 1 pencil sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Mole (with house in background) [reidentification: short-tailed shrew], 1 pencil and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Mole head, lower view [reidentification: gopher], n.d.; 1 watercolor and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Mole jaws and teeth [reidentification: raccoon], 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Mole skull, lower view [reidentification: groundhog], 1 watercolor and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Monotropa uniflora L., n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Orchis spectabilis L., n.d.; 1 pencil sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Osmorhiza longistylis Torr., n.d.; 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Podophyllum peltatum, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Pogonia seedling, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Populus grandidentata, 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Pendant catkins.
  - Profile of a man, n.d.; 1 pencil sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Pyrola Maculata L., n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Spotted wintergreen.
  - Rat or Mouse [reidentification: gopher (the "stones" are inverted cheek pouches)], 1798; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    "A Kind of a Rat or Mouse killed in Indian Countries of the North West 1798."
  - Rattlesnake entrails, [1802]; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Benjamin Smith Barton exhibited rattlesnake drawings on May 7, 1802. Several rattlesnake drawings formerly attributed to B.S. Barton were identified in 1988 as the work of Benjamin Henry Latrobe. These drawings are located under Latrobe's name in the finding aid.
  - Rattlesnake internal organs, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Rattlesnake rattles, n.d.; 2 watercolors; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    One salamander and several rattlesnake drawings formerly attributed to B.S. Barton were identified in 1988 as the work of Benjamin Henry Latrobe. These drawinigs are located under Latrobe's name in the finding aid.
  - Rattlesnake segment, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Rattlesnake skeleton, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype XOS)
  - Root, n.d.; 1 pen drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Repeated in #37: Roots for Elements of Botany, B.S. Barton.
  - Roots, n.d.; 1 engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    For Elements of Botany. Note space left in lower left hand corner, where William Bartram's drawing of the root of Podophyllum peltatum was inserted in the plate. See also engraving listed under Bartram, Podophyllym peltatum.
  - Salamander [reidentification: hellbender (type of salamander)], 5 engravings; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    5 impressions. APS has copperplate.
  - Saururus cernuus L., n.d.; 1 pencil sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Saururus Cernuus L., n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Shark's tooth (Carcharadon?), n.d.; 5 folders; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Siren lacertina, n.d.; 1 engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    B. Tanner, sc. APS owns copperplate.
  - Siren lacertina, n.d.; 1 pen and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Siren lacertina, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Skull (animal) [reidentification: weasel family (Mustelidae)], n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Skull, n.d.; 1 engraving; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    APS owns copperplate.
  - Symplocos tinctoria (L.)?, n.d.; 1 pencil and ink sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Tofieldia?, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Flower only.
  - Tooth, fossil [reidentifications: fossilized shark tooth; possibly an elephant tusk; mastodon molar], n.d.; 4 items; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Tooth (?), fossil [reidentification: apparently either a tusk of a pig or an overgrown incisor of a large rodent], n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Tooth, fossils [reidentification: mammoth or elephant molar], n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Tradescantia virginica L., n.d.; 1 proof; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    Colored engraving.
  - Tradescantia virginica. Virginian Spider-wort, n.d.; 1 proof; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Triadenum virginicum (L.) Raf., n.d.; 2 watercolors; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Trichechi rosmari [reidentificaiton: skulls of walrus and dugong], 1 watercolor and ink drawing; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
    Walrus skull; Also skull of dugong. Two very light pencil drawings on back.
  - Unidentified botanical drawings, n.d.; 4 items; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Unidentified botanical drawings, n.d.; 1 sketch; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
  - Unidentified, n.d.; 2 items; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815 (Othertype OS)
    2 sketches: 1) Flower; 2) Anatomical detail.
  - Battle gentian, n.d.; 1 watercolor; Barton: [Matthias?]
    "I send you a rough, unfinished drawing of a Plant which I found on the Bank of our Creek, Connestoga, a few Days since, - Yet it is accurate"
  - Acnida cannabina, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl.XXIX, figs.1 and 2. Acnida cannabina L.
  - Aesculus alba, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    See "Esculus alba." Elements, pl. XV. Aesculus Parviflora Walt.
  - Aesculus parviflora, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William
    See "Esculus parviflora," with sketches of Aesculus flava, Aesculus pavia. Elements, pl. XV. Shallus, sc.
  - Aesculus polygamia, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
    Colored. Bart. Jour. Trenchard, sc.
  - Alligator, n.d.; 1 ink and wash drawing; Bartram, William
    Possibly related to Barton's 1812 essay on the alligator.
  - Amaryllis atamasco, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William
    Colored. Tanner, engr. [cf. Elements, pl. II. Zephranthes atamasco (L.) Herb.]
  - An Aquatic Plant [Brasenia purpurea ( Mich) Casp.], n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
  - Anonymos [i.e. Chrysobalanus], n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
    Colored. On same print: Kalmea celiata. Plate. Trenchard, sc.
  - Arethusa divaricata, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
    Pen sketch with Philadelphia in background.
  - Arethusa superba, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Note in WB's hand: "Grows on high land in Woods or Forests, 12-15 inches high, the flower of a dark Cinamon or redish purple colour. Native of Pennsylvania, New Jersey." Unfinished drawing (?) of Pogonia sp. Additional notes on verso. Also includes drawing of Arethusa medeola with roots.
  - Bartsia coccinea, 1807; 1 watercolor; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl. IV.
  - Betula populifolia, n.d.; 1 proof; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl. XXVII, in part. Proof, before numbering.
  - Betula populifolia, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl. XXVII, in part.
  - Betula populifolia, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl. XXVII, in part. Color plate.
  - Bignonia bracteata, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
    Colored. Trenchard, sc. = Pinckneya.
  - Canna indica L., 1784; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl.VIII, in part. Also includes drawing of Monandria monogynia
  - Cassia marilandica, 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Classified in Andria monogynia. Also Gerardia flava, Didynamia angiospermia, and Cucubalus stellatus. Cucubalus stellatus used in Elements.
  - Clematis crispa, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
  - Cleome pentaphylla, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Tynandropsis pentaphylla DC. Elements, pl.XXVI.
  - Collinsonia canadensis L., n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl. IX, fig. 3 reversed.
  - Commelina virginica?, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Elements, pl. X, fig. 1.
  - Cornus florida L., n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
    Plate. Tanner, sc.
  - Cornus florida L., n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William (Othertype OS)
    Colored. Intended for Decades, which was a series, issued ten at a time, of plates of plants with "medical properties" to be a new Materia Medica. They are not known to have been published.
  - Cornus florida, n.d.; 2 items; Bartram, William
    Original sketch and proof. Tanner, sc.
  - Diospyros, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Persimmon
  - Dirca palustris [i.e. palustria] L., n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    Also Arethusa mediola and Pogonia verticillata (Willd.).
  - Echinacea purpurea (L.) Moench, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
  - Elements of Botany. Glossay figuers, n.d.; 1 proof; Bartram, William
  - Esculus alba, n.d.; 1 item; Bartram, William
    cf. Elements, pl. XV. Aesculus Parviflora Walt.
  - Esculus parviflora [Also] Esculus flava [Also] Esculus pavia, n.d.; 1 pen and ink drawing; Bartram, William
    "Esculus parviflora Also Esculus flava; Also Esculus pavia." Aesculus parviflora. Also A. flava; Also A. pavia [Elements, pl XV]. Proof before numbering. Shallus, sc.
  - Esculus parviflora [Also] Esculus flava [Also] Esculus pavia, n.d.; 1 engraving; Bartram, William